在上一节课中，我们讨论了如何描述两个物体的位置
In the last lecture we talked about how we described the position of objects in a two
维度世界。
dimensional world.
我们使用了这个例子，例如机器人，我们创建了一个二维坐标
We used the example, for instance, a robot and we created a two dimensional coordinate
帧。
frame.
我们将坐标框架放在参考位置，我们可以描述位置
We placed the coordinate frame at a reference location and we can describe the position
关于那个坐标框架的机器人。
of the robot with respect to that co-ordinate frame.
我们还谈到了我们如何描述物体的方向;那是机器人的方式
We also talked about how we describe the orientation of the object; that is which way the robot
相对于该坐标系上的轴指向。
is pointing with respect to the axes on this co-ordinate frame.
现在我们要做的是提高复杂程度并引入
Now what we are going to do is to kick it up a level of complexity and introduce the
第三维度。
third dimension.
因此对于大多数机器人而言，第三维非常重要。
So for most robotics the third dimension is really important.
例如，机器人可以在任何类型的真实机器人手中移动
The robots hand for instance, in any sort of real robot, the hand is going to move in
一架飞机，但它也可以上下移动。
a plane, but it is also going to be able to move up and down.
所以我们需要能够描述三维物体的位置和方向
So we need to be able to describe the position and orientation of bodies in three-dimensional
空间。
space.
但是也有很多机器人在三维空间中移动。
But there are also a lot of robots that move in three-dimensional space.
所以我在这里有一架模型飞机，或者一架飞机在空中飞行。
So here I have a model airplane, or course an airplane flies through the air.
它上升而且下降。
It goes up and it goes down.
它可以左右移动，也可以通过多种有趣的方式旋转。
It can move left and right, and it can also rotate in a number of interesting ways.
它可以向上和向下倾斜，它可以像这样偏转，它可以像这样滚动。
It can pitch up and down, it can yaw like this, and it can roll like this.
所以水下机器人是另一个例子，他们有点像这样但不是飞行
So underwater robots are another example, they are a bit like this but instead of flying
他们在空中飞过水面。
through the air, they are flying through the water.
所以这些是今天两个非常重要的机器人类，飞行机器人和机器人
So these are two really important classes of robots today, robots that fly and robots
在水下游泳，他们的运动用三维方式描述
that swim under the water and their motion is described in terms of three-dimensional
空间。
space.
也许这样一个简单的轮式机器人，我们可以通过描述它来实现
Where perhaps a simple wheeled robot like this, we could get by with just describing it’s
位置和它在二维空间方面的方向。
position and it’s orientation in terms of two-dimensional space.